# CHRISTIAN E. GUNNING

(706) 224-7627 • www.x14n.org • research@x14n.org

#### EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

My research explores the spatiotemporal dynamics of real-world systems that are discrete, stochastic, and non-linear. My primary focus is on population dynamics of disease systems, where I use empirical data, numerical simulations, and statistical models to elucidate ecological mechanisms. My work draws upon the theory and methodology of mathematics, statistics, and computer science, as well as chemistry, physics, and earth sciences. I am especially interested in stochastic extinction and persistence, partially observed stochastic processes, and population responses to perturbation. At present, my study systems include childhood diseases in the pre-vaccine era U.S., and mosquito population dynamics in Iquitos, Peru.

I have extensive experience with linear and generalized linear modeling, bootstrap-based uncertainty quantification, frequency-domain and wavelet-based time series analysis, dynamical system simulation using both ODEs and Markov chains, and stochastic optimization. I also have a broad background in machine learning, as well as computer data structures and algorithms. I employ a range of open source computing tools in my research, including the R and C++ programming languages for data visualization, numerical simulation, and statistical modeling, and SQL for data management. I also employ reproducible research tools and best practices, including revision control.

In the classroom, I use real-world examples and student-led inquiry to teach quantitative skills to students from diverse backgrounds and experience levels. I believe that rigorous quantitative training is critical for next generation of data-driven scientists. In particular, I aim to increase student access to and personal investment in probability and statistics, scientific programming, and reproducible research methods.

## **EDUCATION**

## University of New Mexico, Albuquerque

Summer 2014

Ph.D. with Distinction in Biology (Disease Ecology with concentration in Integrative Biology)
Committee: Drs. Helen J. Wearing (advisor), James H. Brown, Melanie Moses, and Erik Erhardt
Title: Population and metapopulation ecology of childhood diseases in the pre-vaccine era United States

## University of New Mexico, Albuquerque

Fall 2009

Masters of Water Resources (Riparian Hydroecology)

Advisors: Drs. Bruce Thomson and Roy Jemison

Title: Estimating phreatophyte evapotranspiration from diel groundwater fluctuations in the Middle Rio Grande Bosque

## University of Georgia, Athens

Fall 2001

Bachelor of Science, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology

Advisor: Dr. James Omichinski

## PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- C. Andris, D. Lee, M.J. Hamilton, M. Martino, C.E. Gunning, J.A. Selden (2015). The Rise of Partisanship and Super-cooperators in the US House of Representatives. PLoS ONE, 10(4), e0123507.
- C.E. Gunning, E. Erhardt, H.J. Wearing (2014). Conserved patterns of incomplete reporting in pre-vaccine era childhood diseases. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1794), 20140886.
- **C.E. Gunning** & H.J. Wearing (2013). Probabilistic measures of persistence and extinction in measles (meta)populations. Ecology Letters 16(8), 985-994.

D.M. Smith, D.M. Finch, C.E. Gunning, R. Jemison, J.F. Kelly (2009). Post-wildfire recovery of riparian vegetation during a period of water scarcity in the Southwestern USA. Fire Ecology 5(1), 38-55.

## PENDING PUBLICATIONS

Mentee co-author: †

- C.E. Gunning, M.J Ferrari, E. Erhardt, H.J. Wearing. Evidence of cryptic incidence in childhood diseases. Preprint available at http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/04/079194. Proc. R. Soc. B (In Review).
- M.R. Vella<sup>†</sup>, **C.E. Gunning**, A.L. Lloyd, F. Gould. Evaluating strategies for reversing CRISPR-Cas9 gene drives. In Prep.
- G. Zilnik†, C.E. Gunning, F. Gould. The Evolution of Fitness Modifiers and Their Impact on Insecticide Resistance. In Prep. Draft available on request.
- **C.E. Gunning**, K. Okamoto, H. Astete, G.M. Vasquez, E. Erhardt, C. Del Aguila, R. Pinedo, R. Cardenas, C. Pacheco, E. Chalco, H. Rodriguez-Ferruci, T.W. Scott, A.L. Lloyd, F. Gould, A.C. Morrison. Efficacy of *Aedes aegypti* control by indoor Ultra Low Volume (ULV) spraying in Iquitos, Peru. In Prep. Draft available on request.
- J. Nightingale<sup>†</sup>, M. Holstad, C.E. Gunning. Temperature-dependence in sewer blockage frequency. In Prep. Draft available on request.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Post-doctoral Researcher

Oct 2014 - Present

Departments of Entomology and Mathematics, NCSU

Raleigh, NC

- · Statistical analysis of Aedes aegypti field spraying trials in Iquitos, Peru
- · Continue development of Skeeter Buster of Aedes aegypti population dynamics simulation model
- · Mentor graduate students in Mathematics and Entomology

# Research Assistant

Jan 2010 - Oct 2014

Wearing Lab, UNM Biology

Albuquerque, NM

- $\cdot$  Conduct original research for publication and assist with grant writing
- · Systems administrator and data manager
- · Undergraduate training and mentorship

## Hydrology Research Technician

Jan 2006 - Jan 2009

Rocky Mountain Research Station, U.S. Forest Service

Albuquerque, NM

- · Conduct original research and prepare technical reports for U.S. Forest Service
- · Collect and managed environmental monitoring data

## Plant Genetics Lab Technician

Jun 2003 - Jun 2004

Malmberg Lab, UGA Plant Biology

Athens, GA

- · Isolated DNA, Conducted PCR
- · Design data entry and management system

## NMR Lab Technician

Jan 2001 - Jun 2002

Omichinski Lab, UGA Biochemistry and Molecular Biology

Athens, GA

- · Administer mixed Unix workstation cluster
- · Evaluate linux hardware/software for high-performance NMR data visualization

Jun 2011 (\$2,000). UNM PiBBS Student Enrichment Grant to attend SFI Complex Systems Summer School.

May 2010 (\$500). EEID Conference Workshop travel grant.

Mar 2010 (\$80,000). Center for Evolutionary & Theoretical Immunology (CETI) Seed Grant, Waning Immunity in Influenza and Whooping Cough, Contributing author.

Aug 2009 ( $\approx$ \$50,000). Program in Interdisciplinary Biological and Biomedical Sciences (PIBBS), 2 year fellowship.

May 2007 (\$4,400). UNM Graduate Research and Development grant, Hydrological research in the Middle Rio Grande Bosque.

#### AWARDS

Apr 2013 (\$500). UNM Biology Department Scholarship.

Apr 2013 Graduate oral presentation,  $2^{nd}$  place. UNM Biology Research Day.

Apr 2010 (\$500). UNM SRAC travel grant to attend useR 2010.

Apr 2010 Graduate poster presentation,  $1^{st}$  place. UNM Biology Research Day.

## CONTRIBUTED TALKS

- **C.E. Gunning**, A.L. Lloyd. Skeeter Buster Past, Present, and Future: Challenges and Issues in Modeling Mosquito Populations. Society of Vector Ecology. Albuquerque, NM. Sep 2015. SAMSI Program on Mathematical and Statistical Ecology Transition Workshop. Durham, NC. May 2015.
- C.E. Gunning, H.J. Wearing. Appropriate Measures of Persistence in Childhood Diseases. SAMSI Program on Mathematical and Statistical Ecology Transition Workshop. Durham, NC. May 2015.
- **C.E. Gunning**, H.J. Wearing. Reporting rate variation in U.S. cities. UNM Biology Research Day. Albuquerque, NM. Apr 2013.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Measles dynamics in the pre-vaccine era United States: Linking models and data. UNM Biology Brownbag seminar series. Albuquerque, NM. Oct 2011.
- C.E. Gunning, H.J. Wearing. Measles epidemics in pre-vaccine era United States cities: Linking models and data. Ecological Society of America conference. Austin, TX. Aug 2011.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Spatio-temporal ecology of measles. UNM Biology Research Day. Albuquerque, NM. Apr 2011.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Rwave Detecting synchrony of influenza between U.S. states. useR 2010 Conference. Gaithersburg, MD. Jul 2010.

## CONTRIBUTED POSTERS

- C.E. Gunning, E. Erhard, H.J. Wearing. Pre-vaccine era reporting rates of measles and whooping cough. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease (EEID) Conference. Fort Collins, CO. Jun 2014.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Reporting rate variation of acute, immunizing diseases in pre-vaccine U.S. cities. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease (EEID) Conference. State College, PA. May 2013.

- **C.E. Gunning**. Stochasticity, persistence, and extinction in measles (meta)populations. Models of Infectious Disease Agent Study (MIDAS) meeting. Atlanta, GA. Jun 2012.
- **C.E. Gunning**, H.J Wearing. Stochasticity, persistence, and extinction in measles (meta)populations: Are we measuring what we think we're measuring? Ecology & Evolution of Infectious Disease (EEID) Conference. Ann Arbor, MI. May 2012.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Using wavelets to detect synchrony of influenza between U.S. states. UNM Biology Research Day. Albuquerque, NM. Apr 2010.
- **C.E. Gunning**. Linear Modeling of the Response of Groundwater Level to River Flow in the Middle Rio Grande Bosque, Water Year 2006. National Groundwater Association (NGWA) Conference. Albuquerque, NM. May 2007.

## **TEACHING**

## INSTRUCTOR

## **Probability for Scientists**

Fall 2013, UNM Biology and Statistics

- · Course designer, lead instructor
- · Mixed undergraduate/graduate course (primarily undergraduate)
- · Hands-on course covering introductory probability, statistics, and data analysis

## TEACHING ASSISTANT

Biology for Non-majors

Spring 2014, UNM Biology

Statistical Programming

Spring 2013, UNM Statistics

- · Mixed undergraduate/graduate course (primarily graduate)
- · Also guest lectured

# Mathematical Biology

Fall 2012, UNM Biology

- · Mixed undergraduate/graduate course (primarily undergraduate)
- · Also guest lectured

Genetics Spring 2009, UNM Biology

Ecology & Evolution

Fall 2008, UNM Biology

· Assisted in writing course material

## GUEST LECTURER

## Theoretical Ecology

Spring 2015, Univ. of Montana

· Also assisted students with R

#### WORKSHOPS AND TRAINING

Computational Skills for Scientists Training Workshop

Aug 2016, Univ. of Montana

· Guest lecturer

Industrial Math/Stat Modeling Workshop for Graduate Students

July 2015, NCSU

· Guest instructor, student mentor

# Software Carpentry Workshop

Jan 2015, NCSU

· Teaching assistant, guest lecturer

# UNM R Programming Group

Fall 2010 - Spring 2013, UNM

- · Organized and led weekly R programming group
- · Participants included undergraduate and graduate students and professors

## **Ecology Workshop**

- · Teaching assistant
- · NSF-funded graduate training program, part of Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease conference

## **MENTORING**

Spring 2015 - present. Robert Liberatore, Math Education Software Developer

Fall 2015 - present. Michael Vella, NCSU Mathematics Ph.D. Student

Fall 2015 - Fall 2016. Gabriel Zilnik, NCSU Entomology Masters Student

Fall 2012 - Fall 2015. Joshua Nightingale, UNM Biology Undergraduate Student

Spring 2011 - Spring 2012. Nathan Cournoyer, UNM Biology Undergraduate Student

#### CONFERENCES AND PROFESSIONAL EVENTS

Sep 2015. Society of Vector Ecology Conference. Albuquerque, NM.

Nov 2014. American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene Annual Conference. New Orleans, LA.

Jun 2014. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Conference. Colorado State University. Fort Collins, CO.

May 2013. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Conference. Pennsylvania State University. State College, PA.

May 2012. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Conference and Workshop. University of Michigan. Ann Arbor, MI.

Oct 2011. Rcpp R Programming Master Class. San Francisco, CA.

Aug 2011. Ecological Society of America Conference. Austin, TX.

Jun 2011. Santa Fe Institute Complex Systems Summer School. Santa Fe Institute. Santa Fe, NM.

Jul 2010. useR 2010 Conference. Gaithersburg, MD.

May 2010. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Conference and Workshop. Cornell University. Ithica, NY.

Aug 2009. Ecological Society of America Conference. Albuquerque, NM.

May 2007. National Groundwater Association Conference. Albuquerque, NM.

# PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Reviewer, Ecology Letters.

Reviewer, Theoretical Ecology.

Grant reader, Graduate Research Allocations Committee (GRAC). UNM Biology.

#### SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

Fall 2014 - Present. Develop and maintain Skeeter Buster: a stochastic, spatially-explicit, agent-based C++ simulation model of *Aedes aegypti* population dynamics.

Spring 2013. Wrote code, documentation, and tests according to specifications of Drs. J. M. Rowland and C. Qualls for discrimarts: R package for probability distribution estimation.

2010 - 2012, ongoing. Contributor to Rcpp: R package for C++ development.

2009 - 2012. Maintainer of Rwave: R package for continuous wavelet transforms.

2010 - 2011. Contributor to xts and zoo: R packages for time series handling and analysis.

## REFERENCES

## Alun Lloyd

Department of Mathematics

North Carolina State University

- $\cdot$  Post-doctoral co-advisor (in collaboration with Fred Gould)
- $\cdot$  email: alun\_lloyd@ncsu.edu
- · phone: 919.515.1910

#### Fred Gould

Department of Entomology & Plant Pathology

North Carolina State University

- · Post-doctoral co-advisor (in collaboration with Alun Lloyd)
- $\cdot$  email: fred\_gould@ncsu.edu
- · phone: 919.515.1647

## **Helen Wearing**

Department of Biology, Department of Mathematics and Statistics

University of New Mexico

- · Co-author, Ph.D. Advisor
- · email: hwearing@math.unm.edu
- · phone: 505.277.0357

## Erik Erhardt

Department of Mathematics and Statistics

University of New Mexico

- · Co-author, teaching collaborator
- · email: erike@stat.unm.edu
- · phone: 505.750.4424